

## Alaric D'Souza MD/PhD candidate



714-926-4569



alaricdsouza.github.io



orcid: 0000-0002-8744-8136



alaric.dsouza@wustl.edu

### About me ——

Alaric is a final year MD/PhD student at Washington University in St. Louis. He completed his Computational and Systems Biology dissertation research on Microbial Ecology and antibiotic resistance genes in the Dantas Lab. In Fall 2021, Alaric will apply to Pediatrics residencies, with the intention of specializing in Infectious Diseases via a Physician Scientist Training Program. After finishing his training, Alaric hopes to lead his own research group studying microbial communities and host-pathogen interactions.

## Skills -

Software Packages

Adobe Illustrator, Adobe Photoshop, EndNote, LaTeX, Microsoft Office

Programming Languages

Python, R, Bash, Wolfram

Mathematica

Languages English (native)

Hindi (beginner)

Computer Hardware, Machining and Fabrication, Welding

#### research interests

Microbial ecology, bacterial genomics, and antibiotic resistance.

#### education

2014-pres. MD candidate Washington University in St. Louis

M4 with USMLE STEP exams complete

2016-20 Dantas Lab, Washington University in St. Louis

Computational and Systems Biology

2010-14 Yale University

**Ecology and Evolutionary Biology** 

#### research and work experience

2016-20 Dantas Lab Washington University in St. Louis Doctoral Candidate | Ecology of hospital built environment bacteria and

infant gut microbiota.

2015 Dantas Lab Washington University in St. Louis

Rotation Student | Autologous Fecal Microbial Transplant Analysis

2012-14 Powell Lab Undergraduate Researcher | Foraging behavior of Aedes aegypti

mosquitoes.

2013 Gagneux Lab Swiss Tropical and Public Health Institute Undergraduate Researcher | Antibiotic resistance and mutation rates in

Mycobacterium tuberculosis.

2012 Schlesinger Lab The Ohio State University Undergraduate Researcher | Macrophage receptor signaling for Mycobacterium tuberculosis phagosome lysosome fusion escape.

2011 Seva Dhan Mumbai, India

Summer Intern | Treatment of alcoholics and drug addicts. 2011 Course Consulting Canyon High School

Consultant | Course design for AP Psychology and IB Theory of Knowl-

edge.

Mentee of Dr. P.S. Wijewarnasuriya 2009 Army Research Labs Summer Intern | Semiconductor photoresist optimization for infrared

detectors.

### publications

\* authors contributed equally

2021 Destination shapes antibiotic resistance gene acquisitions, abundance increases, and diversity changes in Dutch travelers.

D'Souza AW\*, Boolchandani M\*, Patel S, Galazzo G, Hattem J, Arcilla M,

Melles D, Jong M, Schultsz C, Dantas G, Penders J Genome Medicine | 10.1186/s13073-021-00893-z

2021 Manure microbial communities and resistance profiles reconfigure after transition to manure pits and differ from fertilized field soil

> Sukhum K, Vargas R, D'Souza AW, Boolchandani M, Patel S, Kesaraju A, Walljasper G, Hedge H, Ye Z, Valenzuela R, Gunderson P, Bendixsen C,

Dantas G, Shukla S

mBio | 10.1128/mBio.00798-21

2020 Environmental remodeling of human gut microbiota and antibiotic re-

sistome in livestock farms

Sun J\*, Liao XP\*, D'Souza AW\*, Boolchandani M\*, Li SH\*, Cheng K, Martinez JL, Li L, Feng YJ, Fang LX, Huang T, Xia J, Yu Y, Zhou YF, Sun YX, Deng XB, Zeng ZL, Jiang HX, Fang BH, Tang YZ, Lian XL, Zhang RM, Fang ZW, Yan QL, Dantas G, Liu YH

Nature Communications | 10.1038/s41467-020-15222-y

2019 Genomic characterization of antibiotic resistant Escherichia coli isolated from domestic chickens in Pakistan Rafique M\*, Potter RF\*, Ferreiro A, Wallace MA, Rahim A, Malik AA, Siddique N, Abbas MA, D'Souza AW, Burnham CD, Ali N, Dantas G Frontiers in Microbiology | 10.3389/fmicb.2019.03052 2019 Cotrimoxazole prophylaxis increases resistance gene prevalence and  $\alpha$ -diversity but decreases  $\beta$ -diversity in the gut microbiome of HIV-exposed, uninfected infants. D'Souza AW\*, Moodley-Govender E\*, Berla B, Kelkar T, Wang B, Sun X, Daniels B, Coutsoudis A, Trehan I, Dantas G Clinical Infectious Diseases | 10.1093/cid/ciz1186 2019 Breakpoint beware: reliance on historical breakpoints for Enterobacteriaceae leads to discrepancies in interpretation of susceptibility testing for carbapenems and cephalosporins and gaps in detection of carbapenem-resistant organisms. Yarbrough ML, Wallace MA, Potter RF, D'Souza AW, Dantas G, Burnham CD European Journal of Clinical Microbiology & Infectious Diseases | 10.1007/s10096-019-03711-y Spatiotemporal dynamics of multidrug resistant bacteria on intensive care unit surfaces. 2019 D'Souza AW\*, Potter RF\*, Wallace M, Shupe A, Patel S, Sun X, Gul D, Kwon JH, Andleeb S, Burnham CD, Dantas G Nature Communications | 10.1038/s41467-019-12563-1 2019 Phenotypic and genotypic characterization of linezolid resistant Enterococcus faecium from the USA and Wardenburg K\*, Potter R\*, D'Souza AW, Hussain T, Wallace M, Andleeb A, Burnham CA, Dantas G Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy | 10.1093/jac/dkz367 Sequencing-based methods and resources to study antimicrobial resistance. 2019 Boolchandani M\*, D'Souza AW\*, Dantas G Nature Reviews Genetics | 10.1038/s41576-019-0108-4 2018 Infant diet and maternal gestational weight gain predict early metabolic maturation of gut microbiomes. Baumann-Dudenhoeffer AM, D'Souza AW, Tarr PI, Warner BB, Dantas G Nature Medicine | 10.1038/s41591-018-0216-2 2018 Superficieibacter electus gen. nov., sp. nov., an Extended-Spectrum  $\beta$ -Lactamase Possessing Member of the Enterobacteriaceae Family, Isolated From Intensive Care Unit Surfaces. Potter RF\*, D'Souza AW\*, Wallace MA, Shupe A, Patel S, Gul D, Kwon JH, Beatty W, Andleeb S, Burnham CD, Dantas G Frontiers in Microbiology | 10.3389/fmicb.2018.01629 2017 Draft Genome Sequence of the blaOXA-436- and blaNDM-1-Harboring Shewanella putrefaciens SA70 Isolate. Potter RF\*, D'Souza AW\*, Wallace MA, Shupe A, Patel S, Gul D, Kwon JH, Andleeb S, Burnham CD, Dantas G Genome Announcements | 10.1128/genomeA.00644-17 2016 The rapid spread of carbapenem-resistant Enterobacteriaceae. Potter RF\*, D'Souza AW\*, Dantas G *Drug Resistance Updates* | 10.1016/j.drup.2016.09.002 2014 Malignant cancer and invasive placentation: A case for positive pleiotropy between endometrial and malignancy phenotypes. D'Souza AW and Wagner GP Evolution, Medicine, and Public Health | 10.1093/emph/eou022 published abstracts 2021 Microbiome and immune disruption accompany mouse death in a gnotobiotic mouse model of neonatal sepsis Schwartz D, Wardenburg K, Shalon N, Ning J, Crofts T, D?Souza A, Robinson J, Henderson J, Warner B, Tarr P, Dantas G Journal of the Pediatric Infectious Diseases Society | 10.1093/jpids/piab031.010 2020 The Gut Microbiome and Resistome of Healthy Volunteers are Restructured After Short Courses of Antibiotics Anthony W, Sukhum K, Cass C, Reske K, Seiler S, Hink T, Coon C, D'Souza A, Wang B, Sun S, Dubberke E,

Burnham C-A, Dantas G, Kwon JH

2017

Infection Control & Hospital Epidemiology | 10.1017/ice.2020.476

Open Forum Infectious Diseases | 10.1093/ofid/ofx163.245

Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Multidrug-resistant Organism Contamination in the US and Pakistan Kwon JH, D'Souza A, Potter R, Wallace M, Shupe A, Patel S, Gul D, Andleeb S, Burnham C-A, Dantas G

2015 Autologous Fecal Microbiota Transplantation as a Strategy to Prevent Colonization With Multidrug-Resistant

Organisms Following Antimicrobial Therapy

Bulow C, D'Souza A, Hink T, Wallace M, Reske K, Sun X, Kwon JH, Burnham C-A, Dantas G, Dubberke E

Open Forum Infectious Diseases | 10.1093/ofid/ofv133.479

#### invited talks

| 2021    | 6 mo M presenting with 5 days of fever, emesis, and irritability BJC/SLCH Infectious Diseases Grand Rounds                            |
|---------|---|
| 2021    | An exploration of Emergency Department turnaround time data WUSTL Clinical Informatics Seminar  |
| 2021    | Total thyroidectomy in a 15 yo F with familial adenomatous polyposis WUSTL GI Seminar   |
| 2021    | Angiomyolipoma in a 9 yo F with tuberous sclerosis WUSTL Pathology Seminar  |
| 2020    | 16S rRNA gene sequencing in bacterial endocarditis WUSTL Lab Medicine Seminar   |
| 2019    | Effects of antibiotic prophylaxis on the HIV-exposed uninfected infant gut microbiome WUSTL MSTP Work in Progress Seminar             |
| 2018    | Bacterial contamination on hospital ICU surfaces in the United States and Pakistan WUSTL Microbiology Department Seminar              |
| 2018    | Bacterial contamination on hospital ICU surfaces in the United States and Pakistan WUSTL Center for Genome Sciences                   |
| 2018    | Bacterial contamination on hospital ICU surfaces in the United States and Pakistan<br>American Society of Microbiology Micro          |
| 2017    | Bacterial contamination on hospital ICU surfaces in the United States and Pakistan CSB-MMMP-PMB Interdepartmental Retreat             |
| 2017    | Multidrug resistant organisms on hospital surfaces in the United States and Pakistan Computational and Systems Biology Retreat        |
| 2017    | Longitudinal analysis of ICU surface microbial contamination in the United States and Pakistan American Society of Microbiology Micro |
| 2017    | Effects of trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole on the microbiomes of HIV- infants born to HIV+ mothers WUSTL Center for Genome Sciences     |
| 2017    | Antibiotic Resistance: a growing public health crisis WUSTL Institute of Public Health  |
| 2013    | Drop Team and Rayleigh-Taylor instability Canyon High School AP biology class   |
| 2012    | Mannose Receptor Signaling SUCCESS  |
| natents |   |

#### patents

2018 Store-Easy Automotive wheelchair storage device.

Patent US9937088B2

Guertler C, D'Souza AW, Milgrom R, Hong T, Xiao Y, Nadell S

#### posters

| · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · |   |
|---------------------------------------|---|
| 2019                                  | Spatiotemporal dynamics of multidrug resistant bacteria on intensive care unit surfaces. IMM/MICRO Mini WIP   |
| 2019                                  | Cotrimoxazole prophylaxis increases resistance gene prevalence and $\alpha$ -diversity but decreases $\beta$ -diversity in the gut microbiome of HIV-exposed, uninfected infants.<br>American Society of Microbiology (ASM) Microbe |
| 2019                                  | Longitudinal analysis of ICU surface microbial contamination in the US and Pakistan NIAID/IDSA Infectious Diseases Research Careers Meeting   |

2018 Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan

American Physician Scientist Association (APSA) Midwest meeting

| 2018 | Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan<br>Lake Arrowhead Microbial Genomics Conference                        |
|------|--|
| 2018 | Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan American Society of Microbiology (ASM) Microbe                         |
| 2017 | Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan American Society of Microbiology (ASM) Microbe                         |
| 2017 | Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan 5th annual Global Health & Infectious Disease Conference               |
| 2014 | Invasive populations of <i>Aedes aegypti</i> in Central California<br>Yale Ecology and Evolutionary Biology Poster Session                                 |
| 2013 | The genetics of foraging behavior in <i>Aedes aegypti</i> Cell Symposia: Genes, Circuits, and Behavior   |
| 2012 | Mannose receptor signaling linking spleen tyrosine kinase and MAP kinase p38 in human macrophages<br>The Ohio State University SUCCESS program             |
| 2009 | Relationship of spinning time and speed to photoresist thickness on semiconductor wafers<br>Army Research Labs: Science and Engineering Apprentice Program |

## awards

| 2021    | Gold Humanism Honor Society Inductee   |
|---------|--|
| 2020    | Spencer T. and Ann W. Olin Fellow  |
| 2017-18 | Burroughs Wellcome Fund, Institutional Program Unifying Population and Laboratory-Based Sciences |
| 2016    | BioEnterpreneurship Core Bench to Business Competition   |
| 2015    | IDEA Labs Demo Day Finalist  |
| 2013    | Alan S. Tetelman Fellowship for International Research in the Sciences                           |
| 2013    | Paul K. and Evelyn Elizabeth Cook Richter Fellowship   |
| 2013    | Connecticut Space Grant College Consortium Student Project Grant                                 |
| 2012    | CBC Spouses Cheerios Brand Health Initiative Scholarship   |
| 2011    | CBC Louis Stokes Health Scholarship  |
| 2010    | CBC Louis Stokes Health Scholarship  |

## activities and leadership

| 2020       | Volunteer<br>Helped produce face shields for hospital  | Maker Task Force, Washington University in St. Louis/Barnes Jewish Hospital |
|------------|--|---|
| 2019-pres. | Volunteer<br>Seeing patients as a medical student volunt   | Saturday Neighborhood Health Clinic eer for the free clinic                 |
| 2014-pres. | Yale Admissions Interviewer  Interviewer for Yale College admissions of prospective undergraduate students  Yale Alumni Schools Committee  |   |
| 2015-17    | Physicians for Human Rights  Co-President of club focusing on human rights and political issues that relate to medicine, including health-care for prisoner, refugees, and underserved communities  Washington University in St. Louis Co-President of club focusing on human rights and political issues that relate to medicine, including health-care for prisoner, refugees, and underserved communities |   |
| 2014-17    | Store-Easy Washington University in St. Louis - Sling Health Company seeking to improve manual wheelchair storage in automobiles   |   |
| 2012-14    | NASA Microgravity University (Drop Team)  Vale University Undergraduate research team selected by NASA to conduct fluid mechanics research in zero-gravity   |   |
| 2012-14    | Splash at Yale<br>Undergraduate group teaching short course  | Yale University s to middle and high school students                        |
| 2011-14    | Big Sib<br>Mentor to freshman students at Yale Univers   | Yale University - Pierson College<br>sity                                   |

# professional memberships

| 2021-pres. | Gold Humanism Honor Society            |
|------------|--|
| 2019-pres. | Infectious Diseases Society of America |
| 2016-pres. | American Society for Microbiology      |

# teaching

| 2017-20 | Computational Teaching Assistant   Fundamentals of Biostatistics   Washington University in St. Louis |
|---------|---|
| 2017-20 | Graduate Mentor   Visiting scholars, rotation students, and undergraduates   Dantas Lab               |
| 2017    | Teaching Assistant   Microbes and Pathogenesis   Washington University in St. Louis                   |
| 2017    | Graduate Mentor   IPH Summer Program   Washington University in St. Louis                             |
| 2016    | Graduate Mentor   Eureka Program   Washington University in St. Louis                                 |
| 2013-14 | Lecturer   Origins of Life   Yale Splash  |
| 2011-14 | Lecturer   The Science of Ice Cream   Yale Splash   |